John J. Vrooman Papers
John J. Vrooman Papers
1926-1960
Vrooman, John J.
7.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American historian, novelist, president of the Schenectady County Historical Society (1884-1963). Correspondence, research, book manuscripts, book reviews, lectures, clippings, and photographs of New York State landmarks.
148724
Biographical History
John J. Vrooman (1882-1960) was an American historian and novelist, and president of the Schenectady County Historical Society. Born in Schenectady, New York, he graduated from the University of Arizona, attended Union College, and received an honorary PhD from Hartwick College in Oneonta, New York.
Vrooman held a variety of jobs across the country, including ranch management in Iowa, an investment business in Missouri and a real estate business in Mississippi. He eventually returned to Schenectady and in 1944 accepted the position of Supervisor of Historic Sites for the New York State Education Department, a job he held until 1951. After his retirement, Vrooman lectured in various venues (including the New-York Historical Society) about historic New York State, and remained active in historic studies until his death.
Vrooman wrote several works of historical fiction and non-fiction about upstate New York, including Council Fire and Cannon, a collection of stories about early New York; The Promised Land, concerning the Palatines who settled in the Schoharie valley; and Clarissa Putman of Tribes Hill, a historical novel. An accomplished amateur photographer, his pictures of historic sites illustrate many of his books, and were also used to illustrate material produced for the New York State Education Department.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John J. Vrooman Papers consist of subject files, memorabilia, and writings.
General subject files contains artwork, clippings, correspondence, a few legal papers, photographs, research material, and assorted other topics.
The majority of Memorabilia is in fact negatives of photographs taken by Vrooman; there is also material relating to awards and a few personal papers. There is also a scrapbook.
Writings consists of drafts, reviews, correspondence, scrapbooks, and other items relating to Vrooman's books, lectures, pamphlets, reports, stories, and unfinished works.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Historians; Literature -- American Fiction; New York State; Vrooman, John J. -- Archives.; Authors, American.; Historians -- United States.; Historic buildings -- New York (State); Historic sites -- New York (State); Novelists, American.; Mohawk River Valley (N.Y.) -- History -- Fiction.; New York (State) -- History.; New York (State) -- History -- Pictorial views.; Schenectady (N.Y.) -- History -- Fiction.; Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Lectures.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Authors.; Historians.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. John J. Vrooman.
Inventory
- General subject files
  - Artwork (Oversize 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Engagements (Box 1)
  - Hartwick College (Box 1)
  - Legal (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - New York (Oversize 3)
  - Research material, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards, 1958; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Awards (oversize) (Oversize 2)
  - Negatives
    - Agriculture (Box 1)
    - Animals
      - Cats (Box 1)
      - Dogs (Box 1)
      - Wild (Box 1)
    - Architecture
      - Business (Box 1)
      - Churches (Box 1)
      - Farms (Box 1)
      - Historic buildings (Box 1)
      - Public buildings (Box 1)
    - Birds (Box 1)
    - Butterflies (Box 1)
    - Calamities (Box 1)
    - Cemeteries (Box 1)
    - City scenes (Box 1)
    - Dairying (Box 2)
    - Farm scenes (Box 2)
    - Garden scenes (Box 2)
    - Historic scenes
      - Events (Box 2)
      - Objects (Box 2)
      - Sites (Box 2)
    - Industrial scenes (Box 2)
    - Landscape scenes (Box 2)
    - Livestock
      - Cattle (Box 2)
      - Horses (Box 2)
      - Sheep (Box 2)
    - Machinery (Box 2)
    - Manufacturing (Box 2)
    - Milling (Box 2)
    - Mining (Box 2)
    - Models
      - Children (Box 2)
      - Women (Box 2)
    - Monuments (Box 2)
    - Pictures copied, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Portraits
      - Children (Box 2)
      - Groups (Box 2)
      - Men (Box 2)
      - Women, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Sports
      - Baseball (Box 3)
      - Bathing (Box 3)
      - Camping (Box 3)
      - Fishing (Box 3)
      - Golf (Box 3)
      - Hiking (Box 3)
      - Horses (Box 3)
      - Hunting (Box 3)
      - Motoring (Box 3)
      - Skiing (Box 3)
    - Transportation
      - Air (Box 3)
      - Boats (Box 3)
      - Railroads (Box 3)
      - Roads and bridges (Box 3)
    - Waterscapes (Box 3)
  - Personal Papers (Box 3)
  - Photographs (oversize) (Oversize 4)
  - Photographs (oversize) (Oversize 5)
  - Photography (Box 3)
  - Publications, miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook (Oversize 6)
- Writings
  - Books
    - Clarissa Putman of Tribes Hill, 1950
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Drafts, first, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Drafts, final, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Drawings (Box 4)
    - Council Fire and Cannon, 1962
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Drafts (Box 4)
      - Page proofs (Box 4)
    - Forts and Firesides of the Mohawk Country, 1943; 1951; 3 volumes
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Final draft, 1943; 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Glossy pages, 2d edition, 1957; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Non-glossy pages, 1951 (Box 5)
      - Reviews (Box 5)
      - Scrapbooks, 2 volumes (Oversize 7)
    - The Massacre, 1954
      - Research (Box 5)
      - Artwork (Box 5)
      - First draft (Box 5)
      - Reviews (Box 5)
      - Summary (Box 5)
      - Scrapbook (Oversize 8)
    - The Promised Land, 1958
      - Review (Box 5)
    - Stories of Early New York, 1960 (Box 5)
  - Lectures
    - Historic sites on Long Island (Box 5)
    - The markers speak (Box 5)
    - Period furniture (Box 5)
    - The promised land (Box 5)
  - Pamphlets (Box 5)
  - Special reports (Box 5)
  - Stories (Box 5)
  - Unfinished works (Box 5)